# RAJATH JAIPRAKASH

🗘 rajathjn | in rajath-jaiprakash | 🏶 Portfolio | 🗷 rajathjnx@gmail.com | 🖫 +91-9900852849

# Summary

Site Reliability Engineer II with 3 years of specialized experience in Infrastructure Automation, CI/CD, and Logging/Monitoring pipelines. Achieved over 50% reduction in manual operations by designing and implementing 20+ Ansible roles across production environments. Specialized in building Automation and proven contributor in cross team collaborations.

### Skills

**Programming:** Python, Shell Scripting, C++, Powershell Scripting

Tools & Technologies: Ansible, Elasticsearch (ELK stack), Docker, GitHub Actions, Jenkins, Syslog-ng, Telegraf, In-

fluxDB, Grafana, Prometheus, NagiosXI, OpenSNMP, vSphere, ESXi, KVM Currently Upskilling: Kubernetes, OpenTelemetry, OpenNMS, Terraform

Certifications: The Linux Foundation: LFS162, Red Hat Certified Engineer (EX294)

# Work Experience

## Akamai Technologies | Site Reliability Engineer 2

Oct 2024 - Present

- Architected end-to-end CI/CD pipelines for our Access Border Routers by integrating it with our AAA Simulators
  and custom deployment scripts in collaboration with our QA team, making the process 4x faster and reduced our
  downtime to just 30 seconds.
- Engineered fault-tolerant system by developing **Python** based auto-remediation scripts for **8 critical services**, significantly reduced manual recovery procedures and improved service availability.
- Identified, Troubleshot and Solved a Business critical logging incident which impacted our **6WIND VSRs**, across **18 Distributed Edge sites**.

#### Akamai Technologies | Site Reliability Engineer

July 2022 - Oct 2024

- Improved our deployment workflow by crafting **20+ Ansible** roles for automated configuration management, reducing deployment errors and cutting rollout time from days to hours across **4 environments**.
- Executed the complex migration of 18 production logging servers by designing comprehensive transition plan and implementing parallel cutover strategy, maintaining near 100% service availability and processing over 250K+ daily transactions without interruption.
- Revamped our logging infrastructure by optimizing, migrating and upgrading our **ELK Clusters** to efficiently handle **150 GB** of daily logs each, resulting in a **300**% increase in log search performance and enabling real-time anomaly detection for **20+ critical services**.
- Spearheaded DevOps knowledge sharing initiative by conducting 6 technical workshops for 30+ engineers over 3 different time-zones, resulting in 40% fewer deployment-related incidents across development teams.
- Enhanced monitoring for 200+ nodes by implementing hierarchical alerting structure in NagiosXI using InfluxDB and OpenSNMP Collector, reducing false positives and redundant alerts by 70%.

#### **Projects**

## ClipForge - AI Driven Video Processing Pipeline

- Engineered an end-to-end local and open-source automated video generation pipeline by integrating WhisperX, FFm-peg, and AI agents created using Langchain Python. Project has received over 77k+ impressions to date.
- Built AI-based metadata generation, improving **SEO** and content discoverability by **40%**. Implemented automated **CI/CD** testing via **GitHub Actions**.
- Deployed on **Dockerized** Ubuntu containers with real-time **Discord** notification system, supporting 100+ daily video operations.

# Education

## PES University, Bangalore

2018 - 2022

B.Tech in Electronics and Communication Engineering B.Tech Minors in Computer Science and Engineering GPA: 8.99/10